<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HYOLAB</title>
    <description>Data explorer who used to study brain</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 14:20:53 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 14:20:53 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Project: Mobile Transaction Fraud Detection</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this 2-week project, I aimed to try something completely different from what I practiced in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://soyhyoj.github.io/2020/project-research-trend-analysis/&quot;&gt;previous project&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of the text data, there were 6M rows of numbers. Rather than munging the data for purely personal interest, I built predictive models that can potentially address a business solution for mobile fraud detection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a collaborative project done by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mariagaya&quot;&gt;Maria Gayà Fiol&lt;/a&gt; and myself. The data we selected was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/ntnu-testimon/paysim1&quot;&gt;a simulated mobile money transaction log available on the Kaggle website&lt;/a&gt;, generated by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/EdgarLopezPhD/PaySim&quot;&gt;PaySim&lt;/a&gt; based on a sample of real transactions extracted from one month of financial logs from a mobile money service implemented in an African country.
(Reference: E. A. Lopez-Rojas , A. Elmir, and S. Axelsson. “PaySim: A financial mobile money simulator for fraud detection”. In: The 28th European Modeling and Simulation Symposium-EMSS, Larnaca, Cyprus. 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal was to understand the features closely related to fraudulent profit by exploratory data analysis and make good predictions on the unseen data based on our findings. To enhance prediction performance, we implemented different machine learning algorithms including logistic regression, random forest, XGBoost, and neural network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main challenge of this data was to predict its highly unbalanced binary targets. The population of real fraudulent activity among the entire records was only 0.01%. Therefore, it was crucial to detect all possibly-fraud transactions, lowering the false-negative cases(=fail to detect real frauds; FN) even if it means to involve some false positives(=falsely asserting a case as a fraud when it’s not; FP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of this synthetic data is that analysts like us could conduct fraud analytics overcoming the lack of public access to private records. However, its simplicity in feature attributes easily led us to the overfitting of algorithms. As our observation, implementing the logistic regression was enough to detect 99% of the fraud transactions maintaining a relatively low FP rate(6.5%) when introduced ‘class_weight’ hyperparameter to compensate for the imbalance present in the dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/soyhyoj/FraudDetectionPaysim&quot;&gt;Check this repository where my part of the data analysis and moideling is available.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-fraud-detection.png&quot; alt=&quot;confusion-matrix&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/project-fraud-detection/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/project-fraud-detection/</guid>
        
        <category>Mobile</category>
        
        <category>Fraud detection</category>
        
        <category>Predictive Analysis</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>CodeOp</category>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Project: Research Trend Analysis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a neuroscience geek who has recently moved on to the field of data science, it was very clear to me that the first personal analytics project had to be something related to my dear past experience of being a neuroscientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jneurosci.org/&quot;&gt;The Journal of Neuroscience&lt;/a&gt;, a weekly peer-reviewed journal published by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfn.org/&quot;&gt;the Society for Neuroscience&lt;/a&gt;, is probably one of the journals that I have read the most while designing, developing and conducting experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 2-week sprint project was a perfect opportunity for me to leverage common NLP techniques in order to find an answer to my question:
Were the rising topics that I read as trends result of my attentional bias or was there a real fuss about them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-research-trend.png&quot; alt=&quot;term-frequency&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning, this project was meant to be a cleaning-oriented one and I definitely enjoyed the wrangling part a lot. But the best part of this work is that I actually got to visualize some of the most stunning trends I’ve been observing these years: the efforts in academia to defeat the sexual bias prevalent in animal experiments&lt;br /&gt; (Scroll back and check the keywords including ‘male’ or ‘female’ from the graph above. What you see in the graph is the changes in the relative term frequency of indicated keywords during the last 10 years.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3008499/&quot;&gt;Female mammals have long been neglected in biomedical research&lt;/a&gt; and not until recently did the investigators considered female samples for behavioral experiments for the ‘consistency’ of their results. In 2012, I was actually advised not to include female animals for behavior studies since ‘female behaviors are unstable and it can cause trouble when trying to publish the work’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the situation has changed. All the researchers have obligation to justify their choice when the study was based on a single-sex group (at least in the European research centers where I worked). And this inclusion kicked in quite radically around the year of 2016, as the result of this analysis suggests. Probably we cannot neglect the fact that the time coincides with when &lt;a href=&quot;https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/notice-files/not-od-15-102.html&quot;&gt;the National Institutes of Health (NIH) grants started to ask for all applicants to design experiments accounting for Sex as a Biological Variable (SABV)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so the most frequently appeared terms over the last 3-4 years have been &lt;strong&gt;‘female’ &amp;amp; ‘male’&lt;/strong&gt; with a reason. What else did I find from this data?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, rather traditional subjects such as &lt;strong&gt;perception&lt;/strong&gt; (keywords: ‘hair cell’, ‘visual cortex’), &lt;strong&gt;decision making&lt;/strong&gt; (keyword: ‘prefrontal cortex’), &lt;strong&gt;memory&lt;/strong&gt; (keywords: ‘synaptic plasticity’, ‘working memory’) and &lt;strong&gt;brain activity monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; (keyword: ‘firing rate’, ‘action potential’, ‘magnetic resonance’, ‘neural activity’) were captured and they are actually steady-selling topics for over decades with some ebbs and flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project has some room for improvement. Some articles of particular releases were not collected due to API problems. Also, the final selection of terms can be refined by filtering out generic terms like ‘mechanism underlying’, ‘present study’, or ‘significance statement’ (these are not giving any information about the subjects). Lastly, I would like to investigate the possibility to aggregate the popular research terms by topics using modeling in NLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details on how I processed this data: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/soyhyoj/ResearchTrendAnalysis&quot;&gt;check my notebooks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/project-research-trend-analysis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/project-research-trend-analysis/</guid>
        
        <category>Neuroscience</category>
        
        <category>NLP</category>
        
        <category>Trend</category>
        
        <category>Analysis</category>
        
        <category>CodeOp</category>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
